Guide to Records of the Interuniversity Consortium RISM RG 9
New York University Archives
Guide to Records of the Interuniversity Consortium
Bulk, 1965-1969
1962-1975
RISM RG 9
New York University Archives
7.0 linear feet 14 boxes
Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM).
Additional Resources
Additional Resources: Archambault, Jean. "Un Village de Pecheurs (Deshaies) en Guadeloupe." Master's degree thesis for the Faculty of Social Sciences, Economics and Politics, Department of Anthropology, University of Montreal, 1967. (Xeroxed typescript).
Benoist, Jean, ed., Les Societes Antillaises: Etudes Anthropologigues, University of Montreal, Department of Anthropology, 1966.
Cartey, Wilfred G. The West Indies: Islands in the Sun, Camden, N.J., Thomas Nelson & Sons, 1967.
Clinton, Jean. "A Characterisation of the Employed, Unemployed and Employable Population of Trinidad and Tobago," Port of Spain, Central Statistical Office, 1966. (Mimeograph).
Comitas, Lambros. Caribbeana 1900 - 1965, Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1967.
Salisbury, Richard F. "Isolated Mining Communities and Social Development in the Caribbean." Paper Delivered at the Seventh Annual Meeting of the Northeastern Anthropological Association, Montreal, 1967.
Silverman, Marilyn. "Deviance and Conformity in a Caribbean Mining Town." Master's degree thesis to the Faculty of Graduate Studies and Research, Department of Sociology and Anthropology, McGill University, Montreal, 1965. (Xeroxed typescript).
Separated Materials
The original contract and accounting records have been removed from the collection and retained by the Reed Foundation.
Related Material
At RISM:
The Vera Rubin Papers, RG 1
At NYU:
Records of the Medical School Attitude Questionnaire (MSAQ)
Records of the Bolivia Project
Records of the Puerto Rico Study
RISM Vertical Files
Access Restrictions
This material is open to researchers without restrictions.
Additionally, please note that this collection is stored
offsite
, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Arrangement
Arrangement Note
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Ford Foundation Reports
Series III: Annual Reports
Series IV: Teaching Papers
Series V: Field Studies
Series VI: Consortium Seminar Papers
Series VIII: Theses and Reports
Series IX: Miscellaneous
History
The Interuniversity Consortium for Research Training in the Caribbean was founded in early 1966. Administered by the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) in New York City, and the Institute for Social and Economic Research (ISER), at the University of the West Indies, Jamaica, the Consortium developed a collaborative approach to extend scientific knowlege of the Caribbean and to improve the quality of research focused on this area.
Supported by a grant from the Ford Foundation, the Consortium began a sponsorship of research training programs in the summer of 1966. 26 social science graduate students from Brandeis University, McGill University, University of Montreal and Stanford University participated in the field training program during the summer of 1966. Special grants were made available to advanced students working with the University of the West Indies (UWI) in Guadeloupe, Guyana, Trinidad and Tobago. The North American universities provided pre-field seminars on Caribbean studies and post-field seminars for thesis preparation. In addition, UWI conducted a summer workshop on Caribbean society for students who required more basic grounding.
The Consortium was formed with several goals in mind, including interest in furthering inter-national academic collaboration and developing standards of ethics for fieldwork in the social sciences. The North American universities participating as full members of the Consortium agreed that students being sent to the Caribbean for their first fieldwork under Consortium auspices enroll in graduate training in research methods and participate in a seminar on the nature of Caribbean society. The Universities organized their teaching programs so that the knowledge and experiences of one group of trainees were passed on to the next group. The universities also agreed to provide supervisors of research, to participate in scholarly interchanges involving the return of findings to the host countries, to distribute these findings to other member universities and to provide fellowship opportunities for West Indian students who were studying abroad. Finally, conferences were held at the participating North American and Caribbean universities where research and training plans were coordinated.
Scope and Contents
The RISM Guide to the Records of the Interuniversity Consortium spans 5.88 linear feet (14 hollinger boxes). The materials range from 1962-1975, with bulk dates spanning 1965-1969.
Brandeis University.; Ford Foundation.; McGill University.; Stanford University.; Université de Montréal.; Americans |z Caribbean Area.; Caribbean Area.; Grants.; Historiography |z Caribbean Area.; Social sciences |x Research |z Caribbean Area.; Teachers |x Training of |z Caribbean Area.; United States |x Foreign relations |z Caribbean area.; Universities and colleges |x Departments.; Universities and colleges |z Caribbean Area.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1965-1969
  - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Teachers College Columbia University/Dr. Comitas, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Development Dead File, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Trinidad Trip march 17th through March 20th, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series II: Ford Foundation Records, 1962-1969
  - Budget- Ford Year 3, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Category 1- Stipends and Travel Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Category 2- Field Expenses Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Category 3- Preparations of Mat. Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Category 4- Staff Salaries Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Category 5- Co-ordinating Committee, Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Category 6- Development Fund Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Category 7- RISM expenses Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Category 8- Contingency Fund Consortium Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Budget- Ford Year 2, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Category 1- Stipend and Travel Consortium Budget, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Category 2- Field Expenses Consortium Budget,1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Category 3- Preparation of Materials Consortium Budget, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Category 4- Staff Salaries Consortium Budget, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Category 5- Co-ordinating Committee Meetings, Consortium Budget, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Category 6- Development Fund Consortium Budget, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Category 7- RISM expenses Consortium Budget, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Category 8- Contingency Fund Consortium Budget, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Budget- Consortium- Year 1, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Budget- Category 1- Stipends and Travel Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Budget- Category 2- Field Expenses and Equipment Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Budget- Category 3- Preparation of Materials Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Budget- Category 4- RISM staff salaries Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Budget- Category 5- Coordinating Committee Meetings Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Budget- Category 6- Development Fundraising Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Budget- Category 7- RISM direct expenses Consortium, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Ford Foundation Mr. Fox, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation General Correspondence, 1962-1968 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous News from Ford Foundation, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Working Papers to Ford Grant, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Proposal to Ford Foundation for Grant in Support of Interuniversity Consortium, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Application to the Ford Foundation for Grant to the RISM, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series III: Annual Reports, 1963-1969
  - 1967-1968 Annual Report Working Papers (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Documents, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Financial Documents, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Summer Seminars, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Theses and Reports, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1969 Third Annual Report to Ford Foundation (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Teaching Papers, 1966-1968
  - Brandeis, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - McGill, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Montreal, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Stanford, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - University of the West Indies, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - University of West Indies, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Maps, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - Students 1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mid-Summer Seminar- Guadeloupe August 5th-10th, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous North American University Consortium Summer Program 1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series V: Field Studies, 1967-1971
  - 1968 Rejections (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - List of Theses and Reports, 1968-1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Consortium Reports, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - List of Consortium Reports and Theses 1967-1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Reports, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Consortium Seminar Papers, 1965-1975
  - September 1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - December 1975 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - November 1975 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - October 1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - McGill University, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Reports of 1967 Consortium Seminar- University of West Indies July 24-29, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Papers and Reports, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Teachers College, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - University of Montreal, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Brandeis University, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Conference Papers, 1965-1971
  - Plenary Session and Workshop Reports, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Pamphlets, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - U.W.I. Trip: Barbados, Jamaica, and Trinidad 3/28-4/5/1965 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - March 5, 1965 Waltham, Massachussets (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - February 4-6, 1966 Mona, Kingston, Jamaica (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - October 8-9, 1966 McGill University, Montreal (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - December 5, 1966- RISM (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - July 18-23, 1966 St. Augustin, Trinidad (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - March 17 thru 18 1967 Bridgetown, Barbados (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Consortium Committee Meeting St. Augustine July 28, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - July 24-29, 1967 St. Augustine, Trinidad, Tobago (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Consortium Committee 12/3/67 Washington D.C., 1967 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Ford- RISM Meeting- January 1969 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Consortium Committee Meeting April 2nd 1968 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Series VIII: Theses and Reports, 1966-1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Consortium Theses and Reports, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Les Societes Antillaises: Etudes Anthropologiques, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - The Folk Medicine of Blanchisseuse, Trinidad, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Some Folk Medicinal Plants from Trinidad, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous
  - Proposal for the Study of Kingston Harbor, Jamaica, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)